Guide to the Bettye Lane Photographs, 1959-2007, bulk 1970s-1980s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bettye Lane photographs 1959-2007, bulk 1970s-1980s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lane, Bettye
2.5 linear feet Extent: 1200 Items
Photojournalist who has been documenting human rights, women's equality, and environmental issues and campaigns since the 1960s. The Bettye Lane Photographs collection spans the years 1959-2007, with the bulk dating from the 1970s and 1980s. This documentary photography collection consists of black and white and some color prints taken by Bettye Lane during the course of her career as photojournalist. The subject matter focuses largely on individuals and events associated with the women’s rights movement from the 1970s and 1980s. Events include Equal Rights Amendment demonstrations, International Women’s Year marches, and National Organization for Women protests, in major cities such as New York City, Washington DC, Mexico City, and Houston. Also included are photographs of women participating in conferences; notable feminists and other personalities; women at work; and women playing sports. A smaller number of images documents protests and rallies concerning lesbian and gay rights, pro-choice, and pornography. The collection also includes photographs of Bettye Lane covering various events as well as a few portraits of her.
RL.00793
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bettye Lane Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2007.
Chronology List
1959-1962 Attended the Boston University School of Public Relations and Communications
1959-1962 Affiliated with Harvard University News Office
1960 Hired by CBS Television
1962-1964 Photojournalist with The Saturday Evening Post
1966-1977 Photojournalist for the Associated Press and the National Observer
2002 Contributed her work to a group exhibition entitled "'For Which it Stands': The American Flag in Social Protest" at the Smithsonian Institution in Washington D.C.
Collection Overview
The Bettye Lane Photographs span the years 1959-2007, with the bulk dating from the 1970s and 1980s. This documentary photography collection consists of black and white and some color prints taken by Bettye Lane during the course of her career as photojournalist. Bettye Lane has worked for many publications, including The Saturday Evening Post, the National Observer, and the New York-based German weekly publication Der Spiegel. The subject matter of the images in this collection focuses largely on individuals and events associated with the women’s rights movement from the 1970s and 1980s. Events include Equal Rights Amendment demonstrations, International Women’s Year marches, and National Organization for Women protests, in major cities such as New York City, Washington DC, Mexico City, and Houston. Also included are photographs of women participating in conferences; notable feminists and other personalities; women at work; and women playing sports. A smaller number of images documents protests and rallies concerning lesbian and gay rights, pro-choice, and pornography. The collection also includes photographs of Bettye Lane covering various events as well as a few recent photographic portraits of her. The photographs are arranged thematically by topic and in rough chronological order. Other Lane photographs are also found in the institutions referred to in a note below. There is some overlap between the collections, but many of the prints at Duke University are unique images. Authorization to publish, quote, or reproduce must be obtained from: Bettye Lane, 463 West Street, Studio D501, New York, N.Y. 10014. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women’s History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Lane, Bettye; National Organization for Women -- History; Documentary photography -- United States; Equal rights amendments -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminists -- United States; Gay rights movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Photojournalists -- United States; Photographs; Pornography -- Political aspects -- United States; Pro-choice movement -- United States; Protest movements -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Protest movements -- United States -- Pictorial works; Radicalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; United States -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Women athletes -- Pictorial works; Women employees -- Pictorial works; Women's rights -- United States; Sallie Bingham Center for Women’s History and Culture
Related Material
Bettye Lane Photographs, 1969-1981 (1500 items)
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
Bettye Lane papers, 1979-1980 [photographs], 0.2 linear ft. (21 items)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C.
The International Gay Information Center Archives, Ephemera: Photographs, Bettye Lane Series
The New York Public Library, Humanities and Social Sciences Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division
Contents of Collection
- Photographs, 1959-2007, (3 boxes)
  Photographic prints, the majority of which are in black and white with a few in color, document events and notable individuals associated with the women's rights movement during the 1970s and 1980s. Smaller groups of photographs document women at work, women athletes, and other social issues such as abortion rights, gay rights, poverty, and the environment. The last folder contains shots of the photographer, Bettye Lane. The majority of the prints are 8x10 in size, and are captioned on the back by the photographer with the date, subjects, and location. Original folder titles supplied by the photographer have been retained.
  - Marches-New York City, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
  - Demonstrations, 1971-1992, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Conferences and Meetings Misc, 1970-1993, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Lesbian Rights, 1976-1984 (Box 1)
  - Personalities, 1970-1992
    - Abzug, Bella (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Rev. Carol (Box 1)
    - Angelou, Maya, with Coretta Scott King (Box 1)
    - Baker, Ella (Box 1)
    - Brown, Rita Mae (Box 1)
    - Chicago, Judy (Box 1)
    - Chisholm, Shirley (Box 1)
    - Ferraro, Geraldine (Box 1)
    - Friedan, Betty (Box 1)
    - Greer, Germaine (Box 1)
    - Hite, Shere (Box 1)
    - Huarte, Delores (Box 1)
    - Jordan, Barbara (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, Florynce (Box 1)
    - Kuhn, Maggie (Box 1)
    - Mead, Margaret (Box 1)
    - Paul, Alice (Box 1)
    - Rankin, Jeannette (Box 1)
    - Ride, Sally (Box 1)
    - Steinem, Gloria (Box 1)
    - Wattleton, Faye (Box 1)
  - Opposition, 1974-1977
    - International Women's Year Conference, 1977 (Box 1)
    - NOW Conference, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Sports, 1972-1981 (Box 1)
  - Professions, 1972-1995, (2 folders)
    - Air Traffic Controller (Box 1)
    - Aircraft Maintenance (Box 1)
    - Architect (Box 1)
    - Armed Forces (Box 1)
    - Audio-Video (Box 1)
    - Banking (Box 1)
    - Bus Driver (the first in New York) (Box 1)
    - Business Women (Box 1)
    - Camerawoman TV NBC (Box 1)
    - Carpenter (Box 1)
    - Construction Workers (Box 1)
    - Engineers (Box 1)
    - Film Crew (Box 1)
    - Park Ranger (Box 1)
    - Photographers (Box 1)
    - Policewomen (Box 1)
    - Postal Carrier (Box 1)
    - Sound Woman (ABC/TV NY) (Box 1)
    - State Policewoman (first in New Mexico) (Box 1)
    - TV Floor Camerawoman (Box 1)
    - TV Floor Producer (Box 1)
    - UPS Truck Driver (Box 1)
  - Signs and Graffiti, 1970-1982 (Box 1)
  - International Women's Year, 1975-1985 (Box 1)
  - Politics, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Conferences: National Organization for Women (NOW) Regional and National, 1972-1975, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - New York NOW Regional Conference, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Washington DC NOW National Conference, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Houston NOW National Conference, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Atlantic City Regional Conference, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Philadelphia National Conference, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Demonstrations, Miscellaneous, 1971-2006, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Marches for Women's Equality, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Religion and Spirituality, 1974-1984 (Box 2)
  - Men for Women's Rights, 1970-1994 (Box 2)
  - Anti-choice and Anti-ERA, 1970-1978 (Box 2)
  - Poverty and Homelessness, 1972-1984 (Box 2)
  - Politics, 1972-1984 (Box 2)
  - Conferences and Meetings, Miscellaneous, 1970-1985 (Box 2)
  - Lesbians, 1971-1983 (Box 2)
  - Words [newspapers and magazines, sexist ads, shirts, bumper stickers, buttons], 1970-1992 (Box 3)
  - International Women's Year Conferences, 1975, 1977
    - Houston, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Mexico City, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Health, 1972-1989 (Box 3)
  - Professional and Blue Collar Jobs, 1971-1988, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Personalities, 1970-2003, (3 folders)
    - Abzug, Bella, 1970-1995 (Box 3)
    - Alpert, Jane, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Artists, miscellaneous, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Atkinson, Ti Grace, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - Barrett, Rev. Ellen, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Berger, Dr. Judith, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Braithwaite, Yvonne, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Brownmiller, Susan, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Caldwell, Sarah, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Chesler, Phyllis, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Chisholm, Shirley, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Constanze, Midge, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Dubic, Isola, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Dworkin, Andrea, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Ferraro, Geraldine, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Friedan, Betty, 1970-1999 (Box 3)
    - Height, Dorothy, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Hite, Shere, 1976-1981 (Box 3)
    - Kennedy, Florynce, 1974-1987 (Box 3)
    - Jong, Erica, 1978 (Box 3)
    - King, Coretta, 1977 (Box 3)
    - MacLaine, Shirley, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Mead, Margaret, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Millett, Kate, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Morgan, Robin, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Neel, Alice, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Nevelson, Louise, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Old Guard Feminists, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Rankin, Jeanette, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Rich, Adrienne, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Shange, Ntozake, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Shulman, Alix Kate, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Smeal, Ellie, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Sontag, Susan, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Steinem, Gloria, 1972-2000 (Box 3)
    - Wallace, Michelle, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Women in Sports, 1973-1984 (Box 3)
  - Pro-choice Demonstrations, Meetings, and Clinics, 1971-1995, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Uncategorized Photographs, 1971-1993 (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Bettye Lane, 1959-2007 (Box 3)